chapter 10
this is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in the public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay hall
the Wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum Chapter 11 The Wonderful City of Oz
by the green spectacles, Dorothy and her friends were at first dazzled by the
brilliancy of the wonderful City. The streets were lined with beautiful houses
all built of green marble and studded everywhere with sparkling emeralds. They
walked over a pavement of the same green marble, and where the blocks were joined
together were rows of emeralds, set closely, and glittering in the brightness
of the sun. The window panes were of green glass; even the sky above the City
had a green tint, and the rays of the sun were green. There were many people— —men,
women, and children— —walking about, and these were all dressed in green clothes
and had greenish skins. They looked at Dorothy and her strangely assorted
company with wandering eyes, and the children all ran away and hid behind
their mothers when they saw the Lion; but no one spoke to them. Many shops stood in
the street, and Dorothy saw that everything in them was green. Green candy
and green popcorn were offered for sale, as well as green shoes, green hats, and
green clothes of all sorts. At one place a man was selling green lemonade, and
when the children bought it Dorothy could see that they paid for it with
green pennies. There seemed to be no horses nor animals of any kind; the men
carried things around in little green carts, which they pushed before them.
Everyone seemed happy and contented and prosperous. The Guardian of the Gates led
them through the streets until they came to a big building, exactly in the middle
of the City, which was the Palace of Oz, the Great Wizard. There was a soldier
before the door, dressed in a green uniform and wearing a long green beard.
“Here are strangers,” said the Guardian of the gate to him, “and they demand to see
the Great Oz.” “Step inside,” answered the soldier, “and I will carry your message to
him.” So they passed through the Palace Gates and were led into a big room
with a green carpet and lovely green furniture set with emeralds. The soldier
made them all wipe their feet upon a green mat before entering this room, and
when they were seated he said politely: “Please make yourselves comfortable while
I go to the door of the Throne Room and
tell Oz you are here.” They had to wait a long time before the soldier returned.
When, at last, he came back, Dorothy asked: “Have you seen Oz?” “Oh, no,” returned the
soldier; “I have never seen him. But I spoke with him as he sat behind his
screen and gave him your message. He said he will grant you an audience, if you so
desire; but each one of you must enter his presence alone, and he will admit but
one each day. Therefore, as you must remain in the Palace for several days, I
will have you shown two rooms where you may rest in comfort after your journey.”
“Thank you,” replied the girl; “that is very kind of Oz.” The soldier now blew upon a
green whistle, and at once a young girl, dressed in a pretty green silk gown,
entered the room. She had lovely green hair and green eyes, and she bowed low
before Dorothy as she said, “Follow me and I will show you your room.” So Dorothy
said goodbye to all her friends except Toto, and taking the dog in her arms
followed the green girl through seven passages and up three flights of stairs
until they came to a room at the front of the Palace. It was the sweetest little
room in the world, with a soft comfortable bed that had sheets of green
silk and a green velvet counterpane.
There was a tiny fountain in the middle of the room, that shot a spray of green
perfume into the air, to fall back into a beautifully carved green marble basin.
Beautiful green flowers stood in the windows, and there was a shelf with a row
of little green books. When Dorothy had time to open these books she found them
full of queer green pictures that made her laugh, they were so funny. In a
wardrobe there were many green dresses, made of silk and satin and velvet; and
all of them fitted Dorothy exactly. “Make yourself perfectly at home,” said the
green girl, “and if you wish for anything ring the bell. Oz will send for you tomorrow morning.”
She left Dorothy alone and went back to the others. These she also led two rooms,
and each one of them found themselves lodged in a very pleasant part of the
Palace. Of course this politeness was wasted on the Scarecrow; for when he
found himself alone in his room he stood stupidly in one spot, just within the
doorway, to wait till morning.
It would not rest him to lie down, and he could not close his eyes; so he remained
all night staring at a little spider which was weaving its web in a corner of
the room, just as if it were not one of the most wonderful rooms in the world.
The Tin Woodman lay down on his bed from force of habit, for he remembered when he
was made of flesh; but not being able to sleep, he passed the night moving his
joints up and down to make sure they kept in good working order. The Lion
would have preferred a bed of dried leaves in the forest, and did not like
being shut up in a room; but he had too
much sense to let this worry him, so he sprang upon the bed and rolled himself
up like a cat and purred himself asleep in a minute. The next morning, after
breakfast, the green maiden came to fetch Dorothy, and she dressed her in one of
the prettiest gowns, made of green brocade satin. Dorothy put on a green
silk apron and tied a green ribbon around Toto’s neck, and they started for
the Throne Room of the Great Oz. First they came to a great hall in which were
many ladies and gentlemen of the court, all dressed in rich costumes. These
people had nothing to do but talk to each other, but they always came to wait
outside the Throne Room every morning, although they were never permitted to
see Oz. As Dorothy entered they looked at her curiously,
and one of them whispered: “Are you really going to look upon the face of Oz the
Terrible?” “Of course,” answered the girl, “if he will see me.” “Oh, he will see you,” said
the soldier who had taken her message to the Wizard, “although he does not like to
have people asked to see him. Indeed, at first he was angry and I said I should
send you back where you came from.
Then he asked me what you look like, and when I mentioned your silver shoes he
was very much interested. At last I told him about the mark upon your forehead,
and he decided he would admit you to his presence.” Just then a bell rang, and the
green girl said to Dorothy, “That is signal. You must go into the Throne Room
alone.” She opened a little door and Dorothy walked boldly through and found
herself in a wonderful place. It was a big, round room with a high arched roof,
and the walls and ceiling and floor were covered with large emeralds set closely
together. In the center of the roof was a great light, as bright as the sun, which
made the Emerald sparkle in a wonderful manner. But what interested Dorothy most
was the big throne of green marble that stood in the middle of the room. It was
shaped like a chair and sparkled with gems, as did everything else. In the
center of the chair was an enormous Head, without a body to support it or any arms
or legs whatever. There was no hair upon this head, but it had eyes and a nose and
mouth, and was much bigger than the head of the biggest giant. As Dorothy gazed
upon this and wonder in fear, the eyes turned slowly and looked at her sharply
and steadily in the mouth moved, and Dorothy heard a voice say: “I am Oz, the
Great and Terrible. Who are you, and why do you seek me?” It was not such an awful
voice as she had expected to come from the big Head; so she took courage and
answered: “I am Dorothy, the Small and Meek.
I have come to you for help.” The eyes looked at her thoughtfully for a full
minute. Then said the voice: “Where did you get the silver shoes?” “I got them from the
Wicked Witch of the East, when my house fell on her and killed her,” she replied.
“Where did you get the mark upon your forehead?” continued the voice. “That is
where the Good Witch of the North kissed me when she bade me goodbye and
sent me to you,” said the girl. Again the eyes looked at her sharply, and they saw
she was telling the truth. Then Oz asked, “What do you wish me to do?” “Send me back
to Kansas, where my Aunt Em and Uncle Henry are,” she answered earnestly. “I don’t
like your country, although it is so beautiful. And I am sure Aunt Em will be
dreadfully worried over my being away so long.” The eyes winked three times, and
then they turned up to the ceiling and down to the floor and rolled around so
queerly that they seemed to see every part of the room. And at last they looked
at Dorothy again.
“Why should I do this for you?” asked Oz.
“Because you were strong and I am weak; because you are a Great Wizard and I am
only a little girl.” “But you are strong enough to kill the Wicked Witch of the
East,” said Oz. “That just happened,” returned Dorothy simply; “I could not help
it.” “Well,” said the Head, “I will give you my
answer. You have no right to expect me to send you back to Kansas unless you do
something for me in return. In this country everyone must pay for everything
he gets. If you wish me to use my magic
power to send you home again you must do something for me first. Help me and I
will help you.” “What must I do ask the girl. “Kill the Wicked Witch of the West,”
answered Oz. “But I cannot!” exclaimed Dorothy, greatly surprised. “You killed the
Witch of the East and you wear the silver shoes, which bear a powerful charm.
There is now but one Wicked Witch left in all this land, and when you can tell
me she is dead I will send you back to Kansas— —but not before.” The little girl
began to weep, she was so much disappointed; and the eyes winked again
and looked upon her anxiously, as if the Great Oz felt that she could help him if
she would. “I never killed anything, willingly,” she sobbed. “Even if I wanted to,
how could I kill the Wicked Witch? If you, who are Great and Terrible, cannot kill
her yourself, how do you expect me to do
it?” “I do not know,” said the Head; “but that is my answer, and until the Wicked Witch
dies you will not see your uncle and aunt again. Remember that the Witch is
Wicked— —tremendously Wicked— —and ought to be killed. Now go, and do not ask to see
me again until you have done your task.” Sorrowfully Dorothy left the Throne Room
and went back to where the Lion and the Scarecrow and the Tin Woodman were
waiting to hear what odds had said to her. “There is no hope for me,” she said
sadly, “for Oz will not send me home until I have killed the Wicked Witch of the
West; and that I can never do.” Her friends were sorry, but could do nothing to help
her; so Dorothy went to her own room and lay down on the bed and cried herself to
sleep. The next morning the soldier with the green whiskers came to the Scarecrow and said:
“Come with me 4 Oz has sent for you.” So the Scarecrow followed him and was
admitted into the great Throne Room, where he saw, sitting in the emerald
throne, a most lovely Lady. She was dressed in green silk gauze and war upon
her flowing green locks a crown of jewels. Growing from her shoulders were
wings, gorgeous in color and so light that they fluttered if the slightest
breath of air reached them. When the Scarecrow had bowed, as prettily as his
straw stuffing would let him, before this beautiful creature, she looked upon him
sweetly, and said: “I am Oz, the Great and Terrible. Who are you, and why do you seek
me?” Now the Scarecrow, who had expected to see the great Head Dorothy had told him
of, was much astonished; but he answered her bravely. “I am only a Scarecrow,
stuffed with straw. Therefore I have no brains, and I come to you praying that
you will put brains in my head instead of straw, so that I may become as much a
man as any other in your dominions.” “Why should I do this for you?” asked the Lady.
“Because you are wise and powerful, and no one else can help me answer the
Scarecrow. “I never grant favors without some return,” said Oz; “but this much I will
promise. If you will kill for me the Wicked Witch of the West, I will bestow
upon you a great many brains, and such good brains that you will be the wisest
man in all the Land of Oz.” “I thought you asked Dorothy to kill the Witch,” said the
Scarecrow, in surprise. “So I did. I don’t care who kills her. But until she is dead
I will not grant your wish. Now go, and do not seek me again until you have earned
the brains you so greatly desire.” The Scarecrow went sorrowfully back to his
friends and told them what Oz had said; and Dorothy was surprised to find that
the Great Wizard was not ahead as she had seen him, but a lovely Lady. “All the
same,” said the Scarecrow, “she needs a heart as much as the Tin Woodman.” On the
next morning the soldier with the green whiskers came to the Tin Woodman and
said: “Oz has sent for you. Follow me.” So the Tin Woodman followed him and came to
the great Throne Room. He did not know whether he would find Oz a lovely Lady or
ahead but he hoped it would be the lovely Lady. “For,” he said to himself, “if it
is the head, I am sure I shall not be
given a heart, since a head has no heart of its own and therefore cannot feel for
me. But if it is the lovely Lady I shall
beg hard for a heart, for all ladies are themselves said to be kindly hearted.” But
when the Woodman entered the great Throne Room he saw neither the Head nor
the Lady, for Oz had taken the shape of a most terrible Beast. It was nearly as big
as an elephant, and the green throne seemed hardly strong enough to hold its
weight. The beasts had a head like that of a rhinoceros, only there were five
eyes in its face. There were five long arms growing out of its body, and it also
had five long, slim legs. Thick, woolly hair covered every part of it, and the
more dreadful-looking monster could not be imagined. It was fortunate the Tin
Woodman had no heart at the moment, for it would have beat loud and fast from
terror. But being only ten the Woodman was not at all afraid, although he was
much disappointed. “I am Oz, the Great and Terrible,” spoke the Beast, in a voice that
was one great roar. “Who are you, and why
do you seek me?” “I am a Woodman, and made of ten Therefore I have no heart, and
cannot love. I pray you to give me a
heart that I may be as other men are.” “Why should I do this?”
demanded the Beast. “Because I asked it, and you alone can grant my request,”
answered the Woodman. Oz gave a low growl at this, but said, gruffly: “If you indeed
desire a heart, you must earn it.” “How?” asked the Woodman. “Help Dorothy to kill
the Wicked Witch of the West,” replied the Beast. “When the witches dead, come to me,
and I will then give you the biggest and kindest and most loving heart in all the
Land of Oz.” So the Tin Woodman was forced to return sorrowfully to his friends and
tell them of the terrible beasts he had seen. They all wondered greatly at the
many forms the Great Wizard could take upon himself, and the Lion said: “If he is
a Beast when I go to see him, I shall roar my loudest, and so frighten him that
he will grant all I ask.
And if he is the lovely Lady, I shall pretend to spring upon her, and so compel
her to do my bidding. And if he is the
great Head, he will be at my mercy; for I will roll his head all about the room
until he promises to give us what we desire. So be of good cheer, my friends,
for all will yet be well.” The next morning the soldier with the green
whiskers led the Lion to the great Throne Room and bade him enter the
presence of Oz. The Lion it once passed through the door, and glancing around saw,
to his surprise, that before the throne was a Ball of Fire, so fierce and glowing
that he could scarcely bear to gaze upon it. His first thought was that Oz had by
accident caught on fire and was burning up; but when he tried to go near the heat
was so intense that it singed his whiskers, and he crept back tremblingly
to a spot nearer the door. Then a low, quiet voice came from the Ball of Fire,
and these were the words it spoke: “I am Oz, the Great and Terrible. Who are you,
and why do you seek me?” And the Lion answered, “I am a Cowardly Lion, afraid of
everything. I come to you to beg that you give me courage, so that in reality I may
become the King of Beasts, as men call me.” “Why should I give you courage?” demanded
Oz. “Because of all Wizards you are the greatest, and alone have power to grant
my request,” answered the Lion. The Ball of Fire burned fiercely for a time, and the
voice said, “Bring me proof that the Wicked Witch is dead, and that moment I
will give you courage. But as long as the Witch lives, you must remain a coward.” The
Lion was angry at this speech, but could say nothing in reply, and while he stood
silently gazing at the Ball of Fire it became so furiously hot that he turned
tail and rushed from the room. He was glad to find his friends waiting for him,
and told them of his terrible interview with the Wizard. “What shall we do now?”
asked Dorothy sadly. “There is only one thing we can do
return the Lion, “and that is to go to the land of the Winkies, seek out the Wicked
Witch, and destroy her.” “But suppose we cannot?” said the girl. “Then I shall never
have courage,” declared the Lyonne And I shall never have brains
said the Scarecrow. “And I shall never have a heart,” spoke the Tin Woodman. “And I
shall never see Aunt Em and Uncle Henry,” said Dorothy, beginning to cry.
“Be careful!” cried the green girl. “The tears will fall on your green silk gown
and spot it.” So Dorothy dried her eyes and said, “I suppose we must try it; but I
am sure I do not want to kill anybody,
even to see Aunt Em again.” “I will go with
you; but I’m too much of a coward to kill the Witch,”
said the Lion. “I will go to declared the Scarecrow; “but I shall not be of much
help to you, I am such a fool.” “I haven’t
the heart to harm even a Witch,” remarked the Tin Woodman; “but if you go I
certainly shall go with you.” Therefore it was decided to start upon their journey
the next morning, and the Woodman sharpened his axe on a green grindstone
and had all his joints properly oiled.
The Scarecrow stuffed himself with fresh straw and Dorothy put new paint on his
eyes that he might see better. The green girl, who was very kind to them, filled
Dorothy’s basket with good things to eat, and fastened the little bell around
Toto’s neck with a green ribbon. They went to bed quite early and slept
soundly until daylight, when they were awakened by the crowing of a green
that lived in the backyard of the Palace, and the crackling of a hint that had
laid a green egg end of chapter 11